碰
Pung
三条
3 bamboos
九章，小心呀
Watch it
怎么搞的？哪有打牌打成这样？
Do you know what you are doing?
我是照规矩打的
l just play by the rules
乱打一通，真气死人
You're all over the place, damn it
四条，开杠
4 bamboos, Kong
抢杠
Snatching a Kong
清一色，三辣
Full Flush, triple the points
这是你包的
You cover the payouts
不关我们的事
That is not our fault
自己找死
You're looking for trouble
人家九章落地还要开杠
He has 9 open tiles and you still Kong
包一铺三辣
You pay out for the triple points
不见二五六，惨了
lt's a pity losing $256
就是啊，明知大牌还开杠
Right, you still Kong in this suitation
笑话了，抢杠当自摸
No, snatching a Kong is same as
drawing by himself
每位是一百二十八
That's $128 each
三家一共是三百八十四
Which makes $384 for three
抢杠当自摸？
Snatching a Kong is considered as
drawing by himself?
对，抢杠当自摸
That's right
当然了
Naturally
人家摆明是九章嘛
That's obviously 9 tiles opened
是啊
That's right
人家九章你开杠
You Kong even he has 9 open tiles
当然是该你包了
Naturally you should cover the payout
照规矩我只出一二八
That's only $128 for me
这算什么呀？
What is this?
九章下地你要全包的
You should cover the payout
怎么？
What?
九章下地包出冲没有包自摸的
lt doesn't cover for drawing by himself
既然是当自摸
lf it is drawing by himself
我只出一二八，找两块
l am only paying $128
那么其他的钱我跟谁要呀？
Where am l supposed to get
the rest from?
当然是找他们两个人要了
From these two naturally
既然是当自摸
Since l draw by myself
每位一百二十八，对不对？
That is definitely $128 each
不对，当然是你包的嘛
No, it should all come from you
抢你的扛，当然是你包了
You are dreaming, you should pay
你包的，我不管
No, you pay all
我不管那么多
l don't care
总之我要收够三百八十四
l insist on getting $384
我也不管
l don't care either
我只出一百二十八
l pay $128 now
我告你们
l will sue you all
你为什么要收三八四
Why do you want to collect $384
而不是二五六？说
And not $256? Speak
因为我是抢杠胡牌
Since l've scored a hand
by snatching a Kong
牌例上讲明
According to the rules
抢杠当自摸的嘛
Snatching a Kong is considered as
drawing by himself
那么每家一百二十八
That will be $128 each
总数是三百八十四
Totally $384
对
Correct
你为什么不包三八四？
Why will you not cover $384?
因为当她是自摸的嘛
Because she draw by herself
打麻将规定十二章才包自摸
The rules say it should cover the pay
for 12 open tiles
九章为什么要包呀？
Not for 9 open tiles
一二八没有少给她
$128 is enough
也有道理
You have a point
那你们两个为什么不给一二八？
Why don't you pay $128?
不是我们犯错
That is not our fault
又不是她自摸
And she isn't draw by herself
是呀，明明是九章落地
Yes, there's 9 open tiles
为什么要我们给？
Why should we pay?
你们也有道理
You have a point too
你们四个全对
You four are all correct
肃静...
Silence...
本庭听过原告及各被告之证供
Hearing the plaintiff
and defendants' arguments
而且又翻查过呈堂的证物
And having looked at the evidence
经过详细的考虑之后
After careful deliberation
判决如下
My verdict is...
第一被告要付三百八十四块
First defendant should pay $384
因为原被告九章落地
Because the plaintiff falls to ground
by nine tiles
你有责任包输的
You are responsible for paying the rest
而且牌例注明抢杠是当自摸
Besides, snatching a Kong is same as
drawing by himself
对不对
Was l not correct
我早说过不关我们的事
l told you it is not our fault
那当然啦
Of course
原告只能收二五六
The plaintiff can only collect $256
因为摸绝章四条的是第一被告
Because the last 4 bamboos
is draw by first defendent
而不是你
And not you
第二被告以及第三被告
The 2nd and 3rd defendant
各需付六十四
Each should pay $64
因为如果当原告自摸
Since the plaintiff is drawing the tile
by himself
你们一样要输一百二十八
You would have to pay 128 just the same
现在每位六十四
Now it's just $64 each
已经便宜你们了
That is letting you off easy
那多出来的一百五十六怎么算呢？
What about the outstanding $156?
本席充公
That is confiscated by this court
那有这样的？...
ls that reasonable?
不得上诉，退庭
No appeal. Court is adjourned
各位麻将高手
Dear mahjong experts
本港雀林盛事
The great event of mahjong for Hong Kong
四年一度的雀爷名衔战
The competition held every 4 years
又到了决赛的阶段
Has come to the finals
有资格问鼎本届雀爷的麻将大师
Our very eligible contestant
有已经禅联了两届的赌业巨子
The gambling magnate and twice champion
丘本立先生
Mr Yau Bun Lap
专诚来港参赛的美国雀王
The mahjong king from United States
徐成义先生
Mr Tsui Sing Yee
上海赌霸陈大文先生
Mr Chan Tai Min, Shanghai gambling king
最后一位是年轻有为
Lastly, the young, successful
十大杰出青年之一的郭柱先生
Mr Kwok Chu,
one of our Ten Outstanding Youth
本届的雀爷名衔战打法有三种
There are three winning strategies
for this year
是盲章，暗章和正章
lt is blind, hidden and normal strategy
四位参赛者在这三种打法里面
Any contestant using such strategies
能够连续胡出八番牌各一铺
To continuously win 8 points...
就可以成为全港麻将权威
Will be Hong Kong's mahjong authority
也就是雀爷名衔的得主
And crowned the King of Mahjong
东
East
南
South
我的北
North
不要动
l won't move from here
第一铺是盲章
The first round is blind strategy
九条
Nine bamboos
碰
Pung
红中
Red Dragon
北风
North Wind
六条
6 bamboos
四条
4 bamboos
怎么又是六条？
6 bamboos again
三条
3 bamboos
坎坎胡，八番
All sets, 8 points
第二铺是暗章
The second round is hidden strategy
六筒，有没有人要？
6 Circles. Anyone?
五筒，有没有人要？
5 Circles. Anyone?
要
Me
一万，有没有人要？
Ten thousand. Anyone?
三条，有没有人要？
3 bamboos. Anyone?
四万，有没有人要？
Forty thousand. Anyone?
一条
1 bamboo
碰
Pung
混一色，对对胡，东风，发财
Full Flush, All sets, East wind
and Green Dragon
八番双辣
8 points
对不起，我也要一条
Sorry, l want 1 bamboo also
清一色，八番
Full Flush, 8 points
难道你认得这些牌吗？
Could it be you recognize
these mahjong tiles?
三六九条都不听
Why you didn't ask for 3,6,9 bamboos
你单吊一条？
You ask 1 bamboo?
还有三六九条吗？
ls there 3,6,9 bamboos left?
三九条
3 and 9 bamboos
三六条
3 and 6 bamboos
一只六条一对九条
One 6 bamboos and a pair of 9 bamboos
三六条
3 and 6 bamboos
六九条
6 and 9 bamboos
三条
3 bamboos
一共十二章牌都齐
All 12 tiles are out
我不是认识牌
l don't recognize the mahjong pieces
是记得牌
l remember them
第三铺是正章
The third round is normal strategy
红中
Red Dragon
碰
Pung
包发财啊
You will cover the payout for
discard Green Dragon
西风
West wind
碰
Pung
北
North
碰
Pung
九万
Ninety thousand
摸了一章群龙夺宝回来
l draw a tile that everyone wanted
碰
Pung
轮都轮到我胡一次了吧
lts about time l won
不对，吃胡要轮着来
Whoa whoa, it should be my turn
我这招叫做打劫红毛鬼
This is called ''rob the English...
进贡法兰西
and give it to France''
截上截
Eventually l get it
果然你们三家都叫绝章三万
All of you vying for
the last Thirty thousand tile
对不起，我自己也要
Sorry, that is for me too
清一色，双辣
Full Flush, double the points
我们老板真有一手
Our boss is the best
恭喜丘本立先生再度成为本届雀爷
Congratulations to Mr Yau, our winner
依照大会条例
According to the rules
禅联三届的人
The winner for 3 consecutive years
是可以永久保存雀爷宝座
Will maintain the title for good
四年一度雀爷名衔战到此为止
This concludes our competition
很多谢各位来宾
Thank you all for attending
四年以后再见
See you in 4 years
等一等
Hold on
各位
Dear all
四年以后的雀爷名衔战
For the contest in 4 years' time
我决定不参加了
l will not participate
由明天起我将会退出雀坛
l am retiring from the mahjong scene
正正式式退休
Formally
所谓无敌是最寂寞的
lt is lonely at the top
我希望四年以后有后起之秀
l hope there will be new blood in 4 years
代替在下参与这个盛会
To take my place in competition
多谢各位
Thank you for your attention
你要退休？
You are retiring?
为什么事前不跟我说一声？
Why haven't you advised me beforehand?
你不觉得刚才的那个场合
Don't you think that occasion...
最适合宣布这件事？
Was most appropriate for announcing this?
是的
Yes
那么你的麻将馆和俱乐部
Then your mahjong house and club
都预备出卖吗？
...Will be sold?
这些是我几十年的心血
All that constitutes my work of decades
我不会放弃
l will not give them up
那你全都交给我管理？
So you will leave them for me to manage?
暂时还没决定
l have not decided yet
难道有第二个人？
Could there be another?
死胖子，矮子
Fat-so, shorty
你走路不看人？
Are you blind?
我就是因为看人
ln fact l was looking
要不然怎么会撞到你？
Otherwise how could l have
bumped into you?
算了，不要吵了
Let's not quarrel
什么算呀？
Leave it?
他撞了人还那么凶
He is in the wrong, yet is so fierce
兰丝，那怕那个三寸钉
Don't be scared of this shorty
什么三寸钉？
Who are you calling shorty?
你说我？
Are you yelling at me?
说声对不起
Just say sorry
什么？
What?
是你不对嘛
You are in the wrong
我不对？
Me? Wrong?
说啊
Say it
你真的要我说？
You really want me to?
说呀
Say it
要说就你说
You say it
我积奇从来不认输的
l, Jackie never apologize
你不说就别想出去
lf you don't, you are not leaving
不出去就不出去，会死啊
So l will stay, l fear not
大不了再回英国
The worse is l will return to England
对不起
Sorry
我这位朋友小孩子脾气
He is like a kid
我代他向这位小姐道歉
l apologize on his behalf
小姐，真是不好意思
Miss, l am sorry
干爹，媚姨
Godpa, Aunt May
老爷
Master
坐
Have a seat
庄臣
Johnson
我叫你回来是想告诉你
The reason l have asked you
to come back...
我决定退休了
is to inform you that l am retiring
您要退休？
You are retiring?
麻雀馆和俱乐部全交给你媚姨管理
Aunt May will manage
the mahjong house and club
你不要回去念书了
Don't pursue your studies in England
留在这儿帮媚姨的忙，管管帐
Stay and help your Aunt May,
keep the books
麻雀馆不是普通生意
The mahjong business
is a specialised field
不熟悉这行根本没法去做
lt's difficult if you are not an expert
庄臣连一幅牌有多少章都不知道
Johnson does not know anything
about mahjong
叫他来帮忙，那不是...
To ask him to help, that...
我叫他管那儿的帐
l have asked him to watch the accounts
又不是叫他坐馆
Not oversee the operation
他是学电脑的
He specializes in computers
对那些数目字一定很敏感
And should be good with figures
说得那么容易
Easier said than done
我跟了你十年
l've followed you for 10 years
你还是不相信我？
You still do not trust me?
庄臣，以后你就管帐
Johnson, from now the accounts are yours
其他的事由媚姨作主
Aunt May will decide on other matters
是，干爹
Yes
根叔
Uncle Jin
这位是...
This is...
老爷的干儿子
the step son of master
他叫阿辉
His name is Ah Fai
是你媚姨的得力助手
And is your Aunt May's side kick
哦，庄少爷
Oh, master Yau
今天很旺
This is a good business day
一直都是这样
lt's been like this
如果不是这样
lf not for this...
你媚姨也不会要死要活的霸着
Your Aunt May would not have
struggled to grab it
别生气嘛
Don't be angry
你干爹有九间麻雀馆
Your Godpa has 9 mahjong houses
三间俱乐部
3 club houses
你看看
Take a look
日夜都这么热闹，生意好起来
lt's busy like this day and night
每个月都有两百多万的进帐
When it's good we get 2 million
each month
碰
Pung
看着他
Keep an eye on him
马不停蹄，马上就来看着了
You have come to check
without delay, huh !
根叔带我来看看
Uncle Jin is showing me around
说不定以后你就是老板了
You might be the future boss
到时候我牌瘾来了想玩几铺
When l have the urge to play
a couple of hands
不知道可不可以呢，根叔
...would you allow me, Uncle Jin
不敢当，媚姨
You are too kind, Aunt May
在英国好吃好住
You have an easy life in England
何必回来跟我争这口辛苦饭
Why return and vie for this difficultjob
谁跟你争呀？
Who is vying with you?
我是尊重干爹的意思
l respect Godpa's wish
我们这行饭
ln our line of business
你以为那么容易吃的吗？
Do you think it is easy?
光是这两下子就够你学了
Only this would take you
some time to learn
用点心吧
Apply yourself
要不然有人会很失望的
Or else someone
would be very disappointed
有人出老千...
Someone is cheating
丘太太，你找我？
Mrs. Yau, you've been looking for me?
今天晚上有几个大客
There are some big clients tonight
你到上面准备一下
Make the necessary preparations
玩真的还是玩假的？
Are you playing for real?
真也好，假也好
Regardless
总之我要赢
l want to win
好，我会办妥的
OK. l will make
the necessary preparations
庄臣，你留十万块钱给我
Johnson, leave me $100,000
干什么？我已经结好帐了
For what? l have closed the book
不是要等你干爹开口你才肯给吧？
Would it take Godpa to instruct you?
庄少爷
Master Yau
你就照媚姨的意思去做吧
Do as your Aunt May says
拿着鸡毛当令箭
Playing the boss
今晚这两个家伙有灾受了
These two guys are in trouble tonight
九筒
9 circles
你媚姨现在向阿辉要九条
Aunt May is asking Ah Fai for 9 bamboos
九条
9 bamboos
碰
Pung
又要发财了
She wants Green Dragon again
五筒
5 circles
这一章
This tile...
打啦
Go ahead
怎么打得出去呢
How can you play like this?
又动手脚了
There you go again
算了吧，弃权了
Forget it, give it up
混一色对对胡自摸发财
Full Flush, All sets
刚刚好八番
Eight points
发财你也摸得着
You are lucky to draw the Green Dragon
这怎么打得过你呀
How can we beat you
真是，听四章牌都胡不过你
l lost even though
l get the good combination
还怎么打呀
How can we beat you
碰
Pung
这一铺媚姨拆牌给阿辉吃
Your Aunt May is favouring Ah Fai's game
东
East
碰
Pung
两番
Two points
怎么搞的？
What has happened?
你看我这幅牌多漂亮？
Look how beautifully l am set up !
我也漂亮啊
Me too
你怎么这么打牌？
Why do you play like this?
你什么牌？
What do you have?
我看看
Let me see
你看我的牌干什么？
Why do you look at mine?
你管我打什么牌？
What do you care how l play?
你教我打啊
You show me
难道我打八筒啊？
Did you want me to discard 8 Circles?
打下一铺吧
Play the next game
别乱打，九章了
Don't mess around
干吗那是假的
He is faking it
二万
Twenty thousand
碰
Pung
这回轮到你包十二章了
This time you will lose
六万
Sixty thousand
四条
4 bamboos
摸来了
l get it
我以为要包自摸
l thought l had to cover all winnings
原来还有钱收啊
But it looks l have money to collect
四圈都不开胡
You didn't win in four rounds
一开胡就来个诈胡
Foul in the opening round
这间弹子房是郭柱开的
This joint was started by Mr. Kwok Chu
你媚姨时常上来
Your Aunt May comes frequently
根叔，她是不是上来打弹子
Uncle Jin, she has not come for the games
她醉翁之意不在酒
Her interest is not in the games
明白吗？
Do you get it?
真厉害
You are good
谁？
Who is it?
救命呀...
Help ...
郭先生
Mr. Kwok
你是谁？
Who are you?
他是我们少爷的朋友
He is our young master's friend
我是问你？
l am asking you
我叫JackyChan
l am Jacky Chan
媚姨
Aunt May
庄少爷
Master Yau
你怎么会到这儿来玩？
Why have you come here?
我不来
lf l didn't come
怎么看得见这么好的戏？
Would l have seen such a good show?
少爷
Young Master
难道你不知道你干妈
Don't you know your Godma
要开一间弹子房吗？
Wants to run a pool joint as well?
原来干妈想开...
So Godma wants to open ...
我是说开弹子房
l am saying open a pool joint
怪不得老来找郭先生
No wonder she frequently sees Mr. Kwok
你年纪轻轻
Young as you are
得点颜色就想开染房
You are over ambitious
既然你知道
Since you know
就不应该这样对我干爹
You shouldn't treat my Godpa like this
管理麻雀馆
To run a mahjong house
牌术要精，眼要灵，反应要快
You need to be good at the game
& have quick reflexes
还要对付那些千王千霸
And deal with those con men
不是你想像中那么容易
lt is more difficult than you think
我知道不容易
l know it isn't easy
不过我想试一试
But l want to try
是啊，我们少爷那么聪明
Yes, our master is smart
我相信他很快就学会
l am sure he will learn quickly
根叔
Uncle Jin
你也算是打了几十年牌
You have played mahjong for many years
还是拿不到雀爷名衔
But have not been crowned
King of Mahjong
你真的有兴趣？
Are you really interested?
本来没有，现在有
Not before, but l am now
为什么？
Why?
我觉得麻将是一种高尚的娱乐
Mahjong is a high class entertainment
可以训练精密的头脑
lt can drill the brain
灵活的思考
To be agile
又可以敦众睦邻
Widen your network and make friends
培养合作精神
Develop team spirit
那就是说你干爹开麻将馆让人赌钱
Are you saying
your Godpa's mahjong business
是不对了？
... is wrong?
不是
Not at all
只要光明磊落，大公无私
So long as it is transparent and fair
都是正行生意
lt is a legitimate business
只怕有些人借题发挥，伤天害理
Except for those who do immoral things
哦，这是你来抽我的后腿
So you are setting me up
告我的状
Telling on me
我做错什么？
What have l done wrong?
说出来怕你丢脸
lt would be bad for you if l told
庄少爷
Master Chong
我看你是吃不到葡萄说葡萄酸
The way l see it, it's just sour grapes
借题发挥的是你不是我
You are the one trying to cause trouble
不要在这儿针锋相对了
Stop your confrontation now
庄臣，你既然有意思
Johnson, since you are interested
我给你六个月的时间学习
l will give you 6 months to learn
在十月二十七号正午
At noon on 27th October
你和媚姨在麻将台上
You and Aunt May will decide by mahjong
决定谁来继承我的生意
Who will succeed my business
当今的麻将大师
The current mahjong experts
除了你干爹，郭柱
Apart from your Godpa, Kwok Chu
跟回去美国的徐成义之外
And Tsui who has returned to the States
还有一个来无踪去无影的燕西楼
There is a Yin Xi Liu
不过他们都不可能教你
But none of them can teach you
现在我带你去见那个人
The one l am taking you to
就是你干爹
ls your Godpa
当年纵横港澳雀坛的老伙计
Once Mahjong King of Hong Kong and Macau
平五
Ping Wu
麻将这个玩意儿
Mahjong is something
我是好久都不玩
l haven't played for a long time
一个人做了赌徒
A gambler
今天就不知道明天的事
Doesn't know what will happen tomorrow
你知道啦
And you know
要用酒来麻醉自己
He sometimes needs booze
to forget himself
手又抖，眼又花
His hands shake and his eyes are dim
还怎么出去混呢？
How can he prevail?
到后来呢
Until at last
不知道戒赌好
He doesn't know whether to quit gambling
还是戒酒好
Or stop drinking
少爷，你有福气
Master, you are lucky
有福气？
Lucky?
我怎么有福气？
How so?
平五爷这个人
Ping Wu
如果他不喜欢你
lf he doesn't like you
他根本就不理你
He wouldn't bother with you
你看他现在像小鸟似的说个不停
See how he chirps like a bird
快去敬茶拜师，去
Go and thank him as your mentor
不用，不用
You are too kind
你干爹跟我是唯一的老朋友了
Your Godpa is my only old friend
难道我眼睁睁的看着他的钱
How can l stand by and watch...
给人家拿去倒帖呀？
while his money is taken away?
况且那个郭柱跟我很有渊源的
Besides, l have a score with Kwok Chu
全看这一铺了
This will settle it all
不要那么紧张
Don't get so excited
阿才，倒杯酒给平五爷定定神
Pour some wine to steady Ping
是
Yes
杀
Kill
九宝
Nine treasures
筒子像煎饼
Circles look like a donut
条子油炸鬼
Bamboos look like the stick
万子集起来大富翁
Collection of all Character tiles
makes a millionaire
东南西北叫门风
East, South , West and North
are called Wind
大三元叫做白发中
Getting 3 of the Dragon is called
Three Great Scholars
孤家寡人叫单吊
Asking for one tile is called Single Wait
你打我要叫作碰
When l pick up your discarded tile
it's called Pung
三只一样的就算一坎
Three identical tile are called Sets
开档的牌摆在当中
You should put the tile in middle
in Closed Wait
你明白了吧？
Do you understand?
好像明白了
Seems so
那我叫三个高手来跟你研究一下
Then l will have 3 experts
to play with you
这三个人都可以做你的师傅
They all can be your teacher
一番
Yi Fan
两番
Liang Fan
十三么
Shi Sanyiu
喂，快点，到你了
Hurry, it's your turn
怎么站长？
What is it, Captain?
到我？
My turn?
到你总是要停下来
Always have to wait for you
五筒
5 Circles
三条
3 bamboos
吃一章
Need this for Chow
三万，益益你
Thirty thousand for you
怎么啦？站站都要停下来呀？
What's wrong with you? Quick
白板
White Dragon
我胡了，混一色小三元
l go Mah Jongg. Two of Dragon
刚好七番
7 points
怎么搞的你？你是什么牌？
What's the matter with you?
让我看看
Let me see
你一筒为什么不开杠呀？
Why don't you Kong?
什么叫开杠呀？
What is it?
我这样可以对碰
l have two chances to win in this way
这样呢又可以单吊
Also there's a chance to win in that way
你们说我这么打是不是最合理呀
Don't you agree
this is the best way to play?
笑死人了
What a joke
师傅，为什么给我一把刻刀呀？
Teacher, why give me a carving knife?
你喜欢哪一章你就刻一章
You can carve out whatever piece you need
干什么？
What's up?
等多一会儿都不行呀？
Can't control yourself?
我跟你说正经事
l have serious business to discuss
正经事儿？什么正经事？
What serious business?
不要嘛
Stop fondling
你听我说
Listen
我不正在听
l'm all ears
平五爷正在教庄臣那小子打牌
Ping Wu is teaching that kid mahjong
他能教得什么呢？
What can he teach?
一个老醉猫
Old drunkard
如果是燕西楼教他
lf Yin Xi Liu were to teach him...
我倒会有点害怕
l might be concerned
不过也不必给他机会
But still we should not risk it
那个老不死真是食古不化
He is a stubborn old man
当年我放他一马
l let him go once
他今天竟然跟我作对
And he dares to oppose me
这算什么江湖义气？
What kind of gratitude is this?
郭柱，这些钱都是公款
Kwok Chu, this is a public fund
现在全输给你了
lt's all lost to you now
反正也没办法回去见丘老爷了
l cannot face Mr Yau
怎么样也要再赌一次了
Hence might as well risk all in one bet
怎么个赌法？
By which gambling law?
用我这条老命
Put all stakes on my life
值多少钱？
How much is it worth?
今晚输多少就赌多少
All that l've lost tonight
好
Agreed
让让
You stay out
派片
One tile on top
杀
Kill
四大公司泊码头
This doesn't give me any points !
你拿去吧
You take it
我...
l...
开牌呀
Open your tiles
鸳鸯六七四
6,7 and 4 points
你真是倒霉到家了，连命都输掉
You're in big trouble;
lost your life too !
爷爷，爷爷
Grandpa, grandpa
什么事？
What is it?
有人送酒来
Someone just delivered a crate of booze
是郭先生订了一箱XO叫我送来的
A crate of XO from Mr Kwok
拿进来吧
Bring it in
爷爷
Grandpa
那个郭先生送那么好的酒给你呀
Mr Kwok is so nice to you
不要动，拿回去
Return it
打麻将分四个阶段
There are 4 stages in mahjong playing
顾自家，盯下家
protect yourself, exterminate your
骗上家，砍对家
Delude, attack the opposition
师傅，你别教那么多
Teacher, don't teach so much
我连自己都顾不了
l can't even protect myself
你慢慢来嘛，这个不能够心急
Be patient, you can't rush it
麻将这玩意变化多端，趣味无穷
Mahjong is a rich game
with endless possibilities
打得不好的呢
Those less skilled
要靠七分运气，三分技术
require 70% luck and 30% technique
打得好的呢
For the skilled
七分技术，三分运气
They need only 30% luck
不过，没有逢赌必赢的
But no one can always win
你要记住，下场三件事
There are 3 important factors to a game
天时，地利，人和
Opportunity, timing and human factor
什么事？什么事？
What's happening?
平五爷，好久不见了
Ping Wu, long time no see
郭柱
Kwok Chu
敬酒不喝想喝罚酒
l tried to do you a good turn,
you declined
你不记得当年我放你一马？
Have you forgotten l let you off once?
放你的屁
Bull shit
你用甲醇灌得我耳又袭，眼又花
You drugged me
你还串同马老大，牛老二来千我
And consorted with others to cheat me
你以为我不知道？
You think l don't know?
说得好，你现在欠我一条命
Well said, you now owe me a life
你现在是来要我的老命，是不是？
You now claim this old life, right?
老命我没兴趣
l'm not interested in your old life
出来
Come out
一番
Yi Fan
爷爷
Grandpa
你...
You...
你现在该知道怎么做了
You should know what to do now
师傅
Teacher
你闪开，老天爷做事实在没道理
Leave me,
the heavens operate beyond reason
虎落平阳被犬欺
l am a down-trodden tiger
平五爷以前是呼风又唤雨
Before l used to be a famous hero
如今变成了醉鬼
And turned into a drunkard now !
是昏天黑地，昏昏迷迷
Confused and dizzy...
我始终是一个酒鬼
l am a hardened boozer
你再跟我学也学不到什么了
You can't learn anything more from me
现在只剩下三个多月
There are only 3 months left
快点想办法去找燕西楼
Try to find Yin Xi Liu
要不然你输定了
Or you're doomed to lose
嗨    嗨
-Hi
你好吗？
How are you?
不太好
Not so good
平五爷已经让你给收拾
You have fixed Ping
我想那些酒够他醉足半年了
He has enough booze
to last him half a year
我还听说那小子
l also hear, the kid...
派了很多人在找燕西楼
is looking for Yin
他真的找燕西楼？
He really wants to find Yin ?
你打算怎么办？
What are you going to do about it?
有什么打算？
Any plan up your sleeve?
让我去告诉他燕西楼在哪儿
Let me tell him where Yin is
是一个通天小子告诉我的
An informant told me
找到刀疤佬就可以找到燕西楼
Find Scar Face and you'll find Yin
他说那个刀疤佬
He said Scar Face as a rule...
照例在一定好那里吃宵夜
Eats at this restaurant
都说明是刀疤佬了
By definition, Scar Face
绝不是善男信女
ls not a nice guy
我怕他不肯见我们
l fear he might not see us
外头人就不见
He wouldn't see outsiders
自己人就不同了
But for his buddies it's different
你算自己人？
You're one of the gang?
有师傅照着
With teacher behind us
不算十足也有八成
We can pass for one
哪个师傅呀？
Which teacher?
你看看
Look
我背了一个晚上
l memorized it the whole night
头发未干出世迟
Born late with hair still wet
家贫少读五经书
Poor with little education
还望义兄来指引
Hoping brother could guide me
犹记花亭结义时
Remember our brotherly pledge
真的一样
Sounds genuine
还不是为你
All because of you
一六四七
你猜有没有人认得出我是探长呢？
Think anyone will recognize me
as a detective?
有身份证的人都认得出你是探长
Anyone could
为什么？
Why?
第一，你进了屋里还戴着帽
Firstly you wear a hat indoors
第二，这里只有你一个人抽烟斗
Secondly you are the only one with a pipe
第三，现在又不下雨
Thirdly it is not raining
你穿什么风雨衣
But you're wearing a rain coat
不用脱
Keep it on
为什么？
Why?
他的意思是说
He means
当你是露体狂，就更加难看
lt's worse if you're taken for a flasher
对对对
Right...
一六四七，一六四九
1647, 1649
有人到，各就各位
Someone's arriving, take your places
探长，不像啊
Detective, this doesn't look like it
线人说是两个老头
The informant said two old guys
带着白粉来给刀疤佬的
Will come and give cocaine to Scar Face
你知不知道
Do you know why
为什么你做了二十年探员
You have been a detective for 20 years
还没有升级呀？
And yet haven't been promoted?
知道
Yes
因为每次我们跟强盗开火的时候
Each time we open fire on thugs
一定打伤两三个队员
We wound our own guys
还有啊，你lQ零蛋
Also your lQ is zero
不错，探长说得对
Detective is right
快去抓人吧
Go catch your man
等一下，你们现在想怎么办？
Wait, what do you want to do?
知不知道
Do you know why...
为什么我做了三十年的探长
Having been a detective for over 30 years
还升不上去做警务处长？
l am still not a Chief?
不知道
l don't know
因为我没有开除你们
That's because l haven't fired you guys
兄弟
Brother
什么兄弟？
What Brother?
反正是兄弟了
Just Brother
你知不知道我姓什么？
You know my surname?
总之姓什么也是兄弟
Regardless we're brothers
我姓元颜耶律督，九代单传
l am the devil-incarnate
什么兄弟？
What brother?
行
OK
四海之内皆兄弟
All men are brothers
姓什么也是一样，是不是？
Regardless of their names, right?
伙计，普洱
Waiter, Pu er tea
来了
Coming
你们两个是不是来捣乱的？
Are you two messing around?
不是，我们是来找人的
No, we're looking for someone
找人？找谁？
Who?
刀疤佬
Scar Face
刀疤佬？
Scar Face?
对，到底哪个才是呀？
Yes, where is he?
你们不会大声叫吗？
Why don't you call him?
刀疤佬
Scar Face
坏了
This looks bad
大疤，中疤，小疤
Big, medium and small scar faces
全来了，到底哪个才是呀？
Which one is Scar Face?
我是
l am
你就是刀疤佬呀？
You are Scar Face?
我叫刀疤成
l'm Scar Face
成哥，我们是自己弟兄
Brother Shing, we're brothers
有事想请你帮忙
We need your help
成哥
Brother Shing
这两个笨蛋是土包子
These two are bumpkins
不是，不是，我们不是土包子
No, no, we are not
有何为证？
What's your proof?
有诗为证
Poetry recitation
诗怎么说？
What does it say?
这...
Well...
头发生疮糯米池
Boils grow from my hair
家贫...
Family is poor...
家贫赌极都要输
But l keep losing when l gamble
万望...
l pray...
万望阿叔点醒我
You will guide me
犹记花亭结义时
Remember our pledge
犹记蜜桃成熟时
When the fruit is ripe
你们两个来捣乱的？
Are you two messing around?
不是，成哥
No, Brother Shing
他平时懒，这诗没念熟
He is lazy and hasn't memorized it well
你们两个来找我干什么？
What do you two want with me?
是不是想做
Do you want to become...
今年第一百六十八凶杀案的主角？
The 168th murder of the year ?
不是，我们是来找燕西楼的
No, we are here for Yin Xi Liu
燕西楼？
Yin Xi Liu?
是啊
Yes
好了，他跟燕西楼一定是好朋友
Good, he must be friends with Yin
朋友
Good buddies
你知不知道我为什么叫刀疤成？
Do you know why l am called Scar Face?
我早就想问你
l had wanted to ask you
你的脸又白又滑嫩
Your face is fair and smooth
连一颗暗疮都没有
There is not even a pimple
坏在我这儿有
Too bad l have a scar here
这是燕西楼把我害成这样的
Caused by Yin
我发过誓
l swore
要把燕西楼的名字改成刀疤楼
l will scar Yin in revenge
就算做不到
Even if l don't
也要找他的亲戚朋友
l'll find his friends and relatives
姨妈姑姑来补数
To pay for his debt
我们不是他亲戚...
We are not his relatives...
你们准备改名字吧
Prepare to change your names
这可不是闹着玩的
This is no joke
快点走吧...
Let's get out of here...
他们在这儿，快点追
They are here, get them quick
线人说送白粉的怎会变成打架？
Did the informant expect this
to turn into a fight?
不要相信线人说的
Don't trust the informant totally
打架也是犯法，抓人
Fighting is also illegal, make arrests
不许动
Don't move
枪啊
Gun
积奇...
Jackie...
积奇，走啊
Jackie, flee
线人没说有人私藏军火
Nobody said anything about arms dealing
怎么会有人开枪？
Why did they open fire ?
好在还剩一颗子弹
Luckily there's a bullet left
探长，探长
Detective, detective
看开一点，何必自杀
Cheer up, why commit suicide
你告诉我，是谁给你这个消息的？
Tell me who gave you this information
吵醒你了
l woke you
我想见见你
l wanted to see you
你有心要做的事一定会成功的
Put your heart into it
and you will succeed
不要遇到挫折就灰心
Don't give up when faced with hurdles
我不是灰心，是死心
l feel totally hopeless
你叫我到哪儿去找燕西楼？
Where can l find Yin ?!
我明天飞去法国，星期三回来
l'm off to France tomorrow,
will return Wednesday
你来接我飞机
Come and pick me up
来了很久？
Been waiting long?
是啊，一个钟头了
Yes, for an hour
怎么那么迟？
What's the delay?
我临时调班，转了飞机
l switched flights
你的小朋友呢？
Where's your friend?
在那边
Over there
庄臣，庄臣，过来呀
Johnson, come here
我给你介绍，他是我大哥燕西楼
My brother Yin Xi Liu
平师傅有没有告诉你
Has Ping told you
我收徒弟是三不教
l don't teach 3 kinds of people
三不教？
3 kinds?
有没有硬币？
Got a coin ?
有啊
Yes
你伸出两只手指照我的意思做
Show me 2 fingers and listen
干什么？玩猜拳呀
What are we doing?
少开口，听我说
Be quiet. Listen
我放下硬币，你用手指夹着
Try to catch the coin with your fingers
一不教，手钝
l don't teach those slow-of-hand
我刚才不留意嘛
l wasn't prepared just now
再给我一次机会
Give me another chance
二不教，眼慢
l don't teach those with slow reflexes
你可以回去了
You can leave
燕先生
Mr Yin
你回去练到眼明手快
Train your reflexes
再打电话来找我
Then call me
多少号电话？
What's the number?
2374213
谢谢你再说一次
Kindly repeat that
三不教，记性差
l don't teach those who have bad memory
这三件事练不好
lf you can't improve in these areas
你根本就不可能打得好麻将
You can't be a good mahjong player
眼球灵活操第一招
Eyes training - first movement
预备
Ready
向上看，向下看
Look up, look down
向左看，向右看，还原
Left, right, original position
咕K咕K转
Rotate your eye balls
突突眼
protrude your eye balls
眨眨眼
Blink
还原
Original position
眼...
Eye
眼什么？
What eyes?
眼药水呀
l need eye droplets
现在要练你手部的触觉
This is to train your hands' sensitivity
是，师傅
Yes, teacher
这是什么？
What's this?
水
Water
是人都知道是水，什么水？
Yes, but what water?
冰水
lce water
这个呢？
And this?
温水
Lukewarm water
这个呢？
And this?
开水啊
Plain water
不错
Not bad
现在要提高速度反覆练习
Now repeat at high speed
温水，开水，冰水...
Lukewarm water, plain water, ice water
冰水
lce water
温水
Lukewarm water
开水
Plain water
你自己看看
Look for yourself
里面没有水
There's no water
我
Me
我，你
Me, you
我，你，他
Me, you, him
我，你，他，你爷爷
Me, you, him, your grandpa
我你他，你爷爷，你奶奶，你姑妈
Me, you, him, your grandpa,
grandma, aunt
你表哥，你表妹，你舅舅，你姨丈
Your cousin, uncle
你大姨妈，你干哥哥，你干弟弟
Aunt, God brother
我你他，你爷爷，你奶奶，你姑妈
Me, you, him, your grandpa,
grandma, aunt
你表妹，你哥哥，你舅父，大姨妈
Cousin, uncle, aunt
干哥哥，干弟弟...
God brother
我你他，你爷爷，你奶奶，你姑妈
Me, you, him, your grandpa,
grandma, aunt
你表妹，你表哥
Your cousin
你舅舅还有你的妈
Your uncle and mother
我你他，你爷爷，你奶奶，你姑妈
Me, you, him, your grandpa,
grandma, aunt
你表哥，你表妹，你舅父，你姨丈
Cousin, uncle
干弟弟，干哥哥
God brothers
姑奶奶，大姨妈，舅母
Aunt...
外叔公，叔婆
Granduncle, Grandauntie...
说啊，说啊，快点说
Come on, repeat quickly
老太婆，姨公，姨婆
Old aunt, uncle, aunt
三叔公，三叔婆
Third uncle, aunt
说啊，说啊...快说
Come on... say it
三叔公，三叔婆
Third uncle, aunt
你妈的，不说了
Damn it, that's it
不错，就是你的妈
That's it
你终于记得了
You've memorized it
现在教你无影手的功夫
Now to teach you lightning hand
看着我，看着我
Look at me
我要把你衬衫上的扣子
l will target on your shirt buttons
一粒粒扯下来
And pick them one by one
你要用手尽量挡着我
Try your best to block me
是，师傅
Yes, teacher
你说扯人家扣子，原来打人
You're hitting me instead
照我刚才那样做一次，来呀
Do what l just did, come
燕先生，燕先生
Mr Yin, Mr Yin
我眼明手快记性好
My reflexes and memory
通通都练过了
Have been drilled and improved
你可以教我打麻将了
You can teach me mahjong now
这个游泳池好脏，你替我洗干净它
Clean this swimming pool for me
是，燕先生
Yes, Mr Yin
燕先生，那个游泳池洗好了
Mr Yin, the pool is cleaned
那边的草太长了，替我剪一下
The grass is too long there, mow the lawn
要每根一样
They must be of the same height
燕先生，那些草剪好了
Mr Yin, the grass is cut
你的牌在哪儿？我去拿
Where is the mahjong set? l'll get it
看这几天就要起风了
lt's been quite windy these few days
你替我拿把锯
Grab a saw
锯掉那些没用的树枝
And cut the dead branches
燕先生，我只剩三个月了
Mr Yin, l have only 3 months left
你再不教我，我怎么赢啊？
How can l win if you don't teach me?
那你回去吧，不用学
Then leave, you don't have to learn
对不起，燕先生
l'm sorry, Mr Yin
打麻将是讲究心眼手脑四合一
You need to coordinate heart, eyes,
hands and brain
眼明手快记性好你是练成
You have trained your reflexes and memory
可惜你头大无脑又心急如焚
But you're careless and impetuous
如果你不潜心苦练
lf you don't train hard
那就白废我的苦心
You'll waste my efforts
还不如收拾好行李
And it'll be better to pack up
回英国念电脑算了
And return to your studies in England
不行，我一定要打赢媚姨
No way, l must beat Aunt May
麻将是用来陶冶性情，训练身心
Mahjong is meant for recreation
不是用来赌博争胜
Not for gambling or winning
你想麻将打得好
To be a good mahjong player
就要记住这个原则
Remember this principle
知道了，燕先生
l understand, Mr Yin
好了，明天收拾好行李
Right then, pack up the baggage and
搬到我这儿来住
prepare to move in here tomorrow
苦练三个月，看你是龙还是蛇
Train hard for 3 months
to see how you perform
那些树枝还没有锯好
Those branches are not yet cut
做完才能走
Leave after you have cut them
是，燕先生
Yes, Mr Yin
你大哥真是够烦的
Your brother is so demanding
我差点让他玩死
He was so difficult with me
好在我有耐力
Luckily l am patient
他肯教你，你已经是走运
You're fortunate he agrees to train you
不要学上次那个醉鬼师傅
Don't repeat the fiasco
with the drunkard teacher
那样搞法就好了
And it should be fine
他也不想的
He didn't want it that way either
我大哥念过很多书
My brother studied a lot
去过很多地方，见过很多人
Been to a lot of places
and met many people
看不起你，他不会教你
He wouldn't teach you
if he didn't like you
人家明天就上山修行去了
Tomorrow is the start of hard training
今晚千金一刻
Tonight is precious
我也不打扰你们了，再见
l wouldn't disturb you
等等我
Wait for me
我还要回家收拾行李
l have to go home and pack my bags
你回去吧
You may return
我现在帮你去收拾好
l'll go and help you pack
明天早上再回来也不迟
We can still make it tomorrow
你进去高兴一会儿，去
Go and enjoy yourself
这三个月你就住在这儿
You'll live here for 3 months
让你见到的，梦到的
What you see and dream
踢到的，睡到的，闻到的都是麻将
feel, touch, dream and smell
will be mahjong
你跟它们多接触点
Make more contact with them
这样才能进步得快
And you'll progress quickly
知道了，燕先生
l understand, Mr Yin
十赌九骗这句话是骗人的
The saying
''nine out of ten cheat'' is false
骗人？
False?
十赌十骗才是真
Ten out of ten people cheat is true
我今天教你防千之术
Today you'll learn to prevent tricks
打麻将出老千不外乎两种
There are two ways to cheat in mahjong
麻牌俗称捉小鸡
lt's called catching the chick
通常麻牌是在翻牌的时候
When you flip the tiles
认定八章自己算好要的牌
you fix eight tiles that you want
例如八章条子
For example 8 tiles of bamboos
真的很像捉小鸡
lt's really like catching a chick
麻牌的时候
When you do this
不外乎触觉跟手法
lt's all in the reflexes
如果骰子打对了
Roll the dice right
要么自己拿，要么对家拿
lt's either us
or the opposite party to take
现在是五点
Now it is five
那不便宜了对家
Then you wouldn't give advantage
to the opposition
不会，如果骰子打错了
But if you roll the dice wrong
只要过一章牌就全都乱了
Then it becomes a mess
真是这样
lt's really like this
打牌碰到老千并不是一件坏事
Meeting a cheat may not be bad
最要紧的是镇定
The important thing is staying calm
有一次我在酒楼遇到三个老千
l met 3 cheats once
你猜发生什么事？
Guess what happened?
输清光了
All lost completely
这个不停拿筒子
This one is just after the Circles
他就专要条子
And he wants the Bamboos only
还有这家找万子
This guy was looking for Character tile
三个人都做清一色
They all want to make Full Flush
我呢就动也不用动
l didn't make a move
在八圈里面胡了五铺大三元
l win 5 games
with the Three Great Scholars
六铺大四喜
6 games of the Fourfold Homely Happiness
自摸清一色
Full Flush by drawing myself
这招叫做一帆风顺
This is a good tactic
有那儿不对呀？
What's wrong with it?
看不出
Can't see
你注意
Pay attention
我再做一次给你看
l'll do it again
刚才我不是上了七八九筒
Did l not get 7, 8 and 9 Circles
然后是五六七筒
Then 5, 6, 7 Circles
这副牌我根本就胡不出来
l can't win in the set
因为没有眼
since l don't have a pair of Eyes
但是刚才我摸了一章一筒
But l draw One Circle
把它搁在这儿
l placed the tiles here
我就手快一推
Quickly l shift 7 Circles to this side
把七筒一挪，我就有眼了吗
Then l get a pair of Eye tiles
这一招叫做一帆风顺
This is called the shifting technique
南
South
碰
Pung
七万
Seventy thousand
开杠
Kong
杠上番，自摸，平胡
l go Mah Jongg
三番
3 points
你平胡怎么开杠呀？
How can you go Mah Jongg like this?
对呀
Right
我明白了
l see
足足二十四秒
24 full seconds
这招叫做借艇割禾
This tactic is called
''Borrow a boat to harvest rice''
那是在打了几圈之后
After several hands
个个都疲倦才用出来
Use it when all are tired
你这么晚才有反应
You only reacted after so long
牌已经推了，钱也给了
The tiles are mixed up,
and the money is paid
谁还理你？
Who will listen to you?
以后要提高警觉
Keep up your alertness
知道了，燕先生
l understand, Mr Yin
明天我去日本
l am going to Japan tomorrow
你自己勤力练习
Train hard on your own
回来考中期试
Then take the mid-term test
嗨    嗨
-Hi
多喝一杯
One more glass
好的
Alright
玛丽关
Mary Kwan
干嘛？
What's up?
怎么不见你的死党来？
Where is your pal?
你见不到她不开心呀？
You are unhappy because she's not here?
不是，多一点人好玩点
No but, the more the merrier
那就是说我们不能令你开心了
This means we can't make you happy
心照啦
We understand
看，刚说到她就来了
Look, speak of the devil !
那个人是谁？
Who's that?
是人家的男朋友
Her boyfriend
老板
Boss
你不介意我带朋友来吧？
You don't mind l've brought a friend?
不要紧的，我姓赖
No problem. My name is Lai
他的名字很好玩，叫蛤蟆
His nickname is funny though; it's toad
那是我的乳名，叫我查理好了
That's just my nickname, call me Charlie
赖蛤蟆先生，我叫庄臣
Mr. Toad, l am Johnson
庄臣，不必客气，请随便
Make yourself at home
珍妮，和我跳支舞吧
Jenny, dance with me
色鬼老板
Dirty old boss
想跳舞呀？
Want to dance?
我不喜欢这个
l don't like this
你喜欢什么？
What do you like?
不告诉你，你会乱说
l won't tell you, you'll tease me
难道想跟我去九龙塘
Did you want to go to a hotel with me ?
我想回去练打麻将
l want to go home to play mahjong
想打牌也用不着回家
No need to go home for that
这儿不能打吗？
Can't we play here?
二四八，四六八番
2,4,8,4,6,8 Fan
不打那么大
lf the stakes aren't high
怎么配得起我这副麻将呢
lt'll not do justice to my mahjong set
这要两万多块钱一副的
lt costs over 20,000 a set
你一定赢的吗？
You always win?
看看我的战绩
Look at my acomplishments
大四喜自摸斜牌胡三筒
The Fourfold Homely Happiness
大三元小斜牌又自摸
The Three Great Scholars
对对胡万子自摸西风
All Sets
老板赢大钱了
The boss will win big money
十三么胡十三章
The Thirteen Wonderful Lanterns
怎么能不自摸呢？
l must draw to win by myself
九子连环是什么都能胡
Calling Nine Tile Hand
全番子对对胡单吊北风
All sets of Wind
还有
Also
全么九全部碰出自摸九万
All one and nine tiles
清一色叫一四条又是自摸
All Flush
诈胡
Foul
按一下拿牌
Press once to pick the tiles
再按一下洗牌
Press again to shuffle the tiles
电子打骰
Electronic dice-rolling
十三剩四
Thirteen
头胡也要胡，这铺牌这么好
l win in the first game
第一铺啦，就胡个四番
l get 4 points in the first game
老板的牌真的这么好
The boss has a good hand
二条
2 bamboos
碰
Pung
谢谢老板
Thank you, boss
对不起，地胡
Sorry
怎么搞的？
What's up?
不是有歌唱嘛
Wasn't there a song which goes...
开档的牌摆在当中
The center tile here
to be put in Closed Wait
这个看相的真灵
The fortune teller was pretty accurate
他说这个月份
He said this month...
逢单日这间房都对我不利
This room wouldn't be lucky for me
on odd days
是啊
Right
为了公平起见
For fairness sake
我们搬出去打
Let's move outside
老板，可以了吧？
Boss, OK?
差不多了
More or less
在这儿吧
Let's do it here
可以了
This will do
好，好
Alright
真是
Trouble
什么牌
What tile to discard?
白板
White Dragon
碰
Pung
五条
5 bamboos
九筒
9 Circles
碰
Pung
红中
Red Dragon
碰
Pung
包发财
Cover the payoff for the Green Dragon
一万
Ten thousand
我四圈没有胡牌了
l haven't won once in four rounds
跟着你打一万
Ten thousand as well
三筒
3 Circles
陈主任下个礼拜就退休了
Chief Chan will retire next week
不知道找谁坐他的位置
Wonder who will succeed him
没办法啦，谁叫自己是大牌呢
l will get the high score
包也得打，发财
Green Dragon
除非我不胡
l must go Mah Jongg by...
一胡就是大三元
the Three Great Scholars
那就得我包啦
Then l have to cover the payout
我这儿就不用你包
You need not since l'm here
不过害得你做不了主任了
But l make you
lost the chances to promote
该打不打
Damn !
三万
Thirty thousand
四条
4 bamboos
自摸，不好意思
Sorry, l draw the winning tile by myself
换地方
Change the location
又胡了，对不起，赖先生
Sorry again, Mr Lai
真是天助我也，九子连环
Oh God, it's Calling Nine Tile Hand
你们谁打我都不胡
l must Mah Jongg by myself
我打红中
Red Dragon
碰
Pung
碰干什么？
What for?
一会儿你就知道
You'll know in a while
八条
8 bamboos
快点快点
Quickly
西风
West
碰，该我胡了吧
Pung, l would win
这次发达了
l've hit the jackpot this time
每人两千五百六
That'll be 2,560 each
我自摸双辣
l win by double scores
你怎么自摸双辣呀？
How come?
我九子连环全部万子
l'm Calling Nine Tile Hand
我自摸一万不就胡了吗
l draw the Ten thousands tile then l win
我怎么知道是不是九子连环？
How can l be sure of that?
我早就说过，你们谁打我都不胡
l said to you before
我自摸一万不就胡牌了
l will win by drawing Ten thousand tile
我还说我有三个一万
l'm also saying
l have 3 Ten thousand tiles
你信不信呀？赖先生
Don't you believe, Mr Lai?
我不管，我胡的
l don't care. l win
所谓快棋慢马吊
Playing chess fast and mahjong slow
纵高也不妙
Despite good skills you're likely to lose
就是说下棋要慢
That is to say
you should be slow at chess
打麻将一定要快
But quick at mahjong
我在日本买了一部麻将电脑机回来
l've brought a mahjong computer
from Japan
训练一下你打麻将的速度
To test your speed
我现在示范一次给你看
l'll demonstrate once
现在开牌
Setting the tiles
摸牌
Drawing the tiles
打牌
Playing the tiles
上牌
Chowing
摸牌
Drawing the tiles
听牌
Asking the tiles
胡牌
Mah Jongg
我也听说燕西楼
l've heard Yin
教了那小子不少东西
Taught the kid a lot
一个生意人
A business man
又不是吃这行饭
Doesn't need this for a living
不必在这儿惹事生非
Shouldn't create unnecessary trouble
要不要我找人去修理他一下
Do you want me to take care of him ?
也好
Might as well
既然燕西楼叫我下不了台
Since Yin has opposed me
我也不必饶他
l don't need to be merciful with him
那怎么个算法，郭少爷？
How will l be rewarded?
阿辉，你怎么这样跟我说话？
Ah Fai, why do you talk to me like this?
将来丘家的麻将馆全在我手里
When l gain control of
Yau's mahjong business
你怕我待薄你？
You think l will not repay you well?
有这话就行了
That's a deal then
谁游泳？
Who's swimming?
我游得很好的
l swim well
走啊
Let's go
不过人家没带泳衣
But l have no swim suit
我得陪人家
l have to accompany others
借我过桥
You used me
就这么一次，下不为例
This is an exception
去你的
Damn you
一定要有泳衣才可以游泳的吗？
You do need a swim suit to swim
我游给你看，走
l'll show you, let's go
你不去游泳？
Aren't you swimming?
天天关在屋子里对着麻将
l am facing mahjong all day in my room
现在看到蓝天像白板
The sky appears like a dragon tile
绿水像发财
The sea reminds me of that too
还敢去游泳吗？
Would l still dare to swim?
泼死你，泼死你
l'll make you wet
别泼，我投降...
Don't, l surrender
这么坏，我看你敢不敢叫我裸泳？
Still dare to ask me to swim in the nude?
不敢，不敢
No, no l dare not
这样更好看呀
This looks even better
救命啊...
Help
Help !
快进去，别出来
Hide and don't come out
救命啊...
Help
救我...
Help me
快点
Quickly
买定离手
Place your bets
开
Open
慢着
Wait
哇，这么多钱...
Wow, so much money...
开吧
Go on, open
这位老兄，请你等等好吗？
Can you wait please?
为什么要等一下？
What for?
怎么样？受不受啊？
Well, will you take the bet?
老兄，请等一下
Please wait
我们公司是限注的
We have a limit on bets
我以为你们这间公司很大
l thought you were a big company
原来也是小儿科
Looks like it is a small business
等一等
Wait
这铺例外，受你
l'll make an exception and take your bet
这样才对
That's more like it
你们也不一定输
You might win
我来开
Let me open
不要开
Don't
现在不可以拿回钱了
You can't take back your bet now
没有人说把钱拿回来
That's not my intention
是你扒摊的方法不对
The way you count the chips is wrong
有什么不对？
What's wrong?
我金山那边是两粒两粒扒的
ln America we count in twos
扒两粒？
ln twos?!
为什么你要扒四粒呢？
Why count by fours?
两粒，两粒怎么扒？
How to count in twos?
哪有这样的？
ls there such a thing?
这位先生有没有弄错？
Do you know what you are doing?
我没弄错，扒两粒
Yes, count in twos
好，就照你的意思扒两粒
Alright, do it your way
其他的朋友请把钱都拿回去
The others please take back your bets
这一铺就跟这位先生赌
This game is solely for
this gentleman here
摊开二
Two
如果扒四粒的话
lf it were counted by fours
你不就赢了
You wouldn't have won
就是啊，怎么这么笨呢？
That's right, how dumb !
你买三四，叫人两粒两粒扒
You place bets on 3 and 4,
and counting by twos
你一定输的，笨蛋
You're bound to lose, idiot
输钱事小，我再买下一铺
Losing is no problem, l'll try again
这铺是不是两粒两粒扒的？
Count by twos again?
上一铺都是，这一铺当然一样
But of course, like the last game
对不起
Sorry
这一铺要照规矩扒四粒
This will follow the rules
and count by fours
刚才一铺扒两粒
The last game counted by twos
现在为什么扒四粒？
Why count by fours this time?
如果不扒两粒
lf you don't count by twos
上一铺就不该受人家
You shouldn't have taken bets
for the last game
是呀
Right
各位不要吵
Hold your horses
如果郭先生不肯开这一铺的话
lf Mr Kwok would not play this game
大家拿回钱走呀
Take back your money
我相信赌场不止这一间的
l am sure there are other gambling joints
燕西楼，原来你们是串通好的
So you two are conspiring, Yin
千万不要这么说
Don't put it that way
我不过来找点外快买惊风散
l just wanted some money
to calm my nerves
你知道，我不是给人吓惯的
You know, l'm not used to threats
开呀
Open...
好，这铺我照开
OK, l'll entertain this game
好...
Good...
开什么开，赔钱吧
Here, cover the loss
等一下
Wait
净买一个数怎么跟我算？
How do you pay if l bet on just one?
开呀...
Open...
一
One!
连本都输光了
All is lost
燕西楼，你怎么知道我开一的？
Yin, how do you know l have a one?
郭老兄
Old Kwok
就算天下第一赌王也要碰碰运气的
Even the best sometimes depends on luck
赔钱，到此为止
Pay them, game over
好眼光
Keen eyes
好镇定
Very cool
燕先生，我知道你是高手
Mr Yin, you're an expert
不过事不关己，己不劳心这句话
Mind your own business
你该听过吧？
Have you heard the saying?
这句话就没听过
No l haven't
不过时常听人说
But l've heard
路见不平，拔刀相助
lnterfere when there is injustice
那你是存心跟我们作对？
So you're bent on opposing us?
凡事要公平竞争
l want a fair fight
你们又什么可以只手遮天
Why do you want to have absolute power
不给庄臣一个机会呢？
And don't give Johnson a chance?
我是丘本立的太太
l am the wife of Yau
庄臣根本就没有资格跟我争
Johnson is not worthy to compete with me
丘老爷既然要你们
Since it is Yau's intention
在麻将桌上决一高下
You should sort this out
at the mahjong table
那么庄臣就有资格跟你争
Then Johnson is worthy
燕西楼，刚才我已经忍你很久了
Yin, l've been patient with you
你现在你还不识相？
You still push your luck?
我向来是硬骨头
l've always been a tough guy
不懂什么叫识相
And pushed my luck
这三个月来
ln these 3 months
可以教你的我已经全都教了
l've taught you all l can
下个礼拜你就跟你干妈决一胜负
Next week you'll compete with your aunt
我想你该有个心理准备
You should be psychologically prepared
牌打得好不一定能赢
Technique doesn't guarantee winning
还要讲运气，时机
There's luck, opportunity
临场应变决定一切
And reaction during competition
记住，骄兵必败
Remember, pride comes before a fall
庄臣
Johnson
我今天约了刘先生跟黄先生
l've invited Mr Lau and Mr Wonh
两位千门高手
Two experts
算是跟你考毕业试
To test you at the graduation exam
最要紧是镇定
Stay cool
东
East
碰
Pung
南
South
这章白板不能打
l can't discard the White Dragon
四条
4 bamboos
小刘呀
Liu
白先生最近怎么没有来找我们？
Why hasn't Mr Pak visited us lately?
怎么？你很想见他？
Why, you want to see him?
白板
White Dragon
碰
Pung
不好意思，大三元，对对胡
Sorry, All Dragon, All sets
你胡什么我不知道
l don't know what is it that you want
总之我胡白板
But l want White Dragon
混一色平胡，四番
4 points
庄臣的麻将真的有那么好？
ls Johnson really that good?
我这两位朋友绝不会看错
My two friends would not misjudge him
照我看，他都接近第一流
He's near to being the best
是啊，真的
Really
那怎么办呢？
What should we do?
不管他怎么出神入化，呼风唤雨
No matter how good he is
我自有办法让那小子坐不上台子
l'll see to it
he doesn't come to the table
祝你今天旗开得胜
Good luck to you
谢谢
Thanks
师傅
Teacher
您也来了
You're here too !
是啊，你最好多赢一点
Yes, win more
让师傅也开开心
So l'll be pleased
醒目点
Watch it
撞他
Ram him
他们想干什么？
What do they want?
不用怕，玩两手给你看看
Don't be scared, l'll show them
还想逃，撞
Want to escape? Ram him
快点...把他甩掉
Quickly, lest he escapes
别管那么多了
Never mind that
快点把车开出去，开回去
Go back, go back
开出去？
Go back?
你不怕又给郭柱那班人撞
Aren't you afraid of being crushed
你不是说你技术很好吗？
Didn't you say you have good skills?
快点开出去...快点
Back on the road, quickly
好，开出去
Ok, let's go
放心吧，三两下手势就可以了
Don't worry, this will take care of it
不用怕
Don't be afraid
是不是？他们连跟都跟不上
See? They can't keep up
小心点，货车...
Be careful, stop...
好危险呀
Very dangerous !
怎么搞的？死家伙
What? The damned fellow
你会不会开车？退后
Do you know how to drive? Move backward
好呀，甩掉他们了
Good, we've lost them
这是什么地方呀？
What's this place?
大概是天堂边缘
Edge of heaven, l guess
完了
We've finished
这次他跑不了吧，撞他下去
He can't escape now, ram him
没事了，解决了
lts alright now
我们回去收钱了，走...
Let's go and collect our money
本立，他根本就没有胆子来
He doesn't have the guts to show up
不要耽误大家的时间
Let's not waste everybody's time
当他弃权算了
Assume he has given up
来了，来了
He's coming, he's coming
丘少爷来了
Master Yau is here
各位雀林前辈，娱乐界友好
Dear friends of mahjong and entertainment
麻将馆同仁
Our mahjong house
今天请各位到场参观
Has invited you all to witness
主要是决定内子
The game to decide, if my wife...
或者是我干儿子
Or my Godson
来继承在下产业的地位
Will succeed my estate
比赛胜利的一方
The winner
将会全权管理在下九间麻将馆
Will run my 9 mahjong houses
三间俱乐部
And my 3 clubs
无论是谁赢都好
Whoever wins
请各界友好多多提携指导
l hope will have your support
为了内子跟我干儿子公平竞赛
To ensure fair competition
我专诚在美国请了徐成义先生回来
l have specially invited
Mr Tsui from the States
跟大家一起临场监督
To monitor the game with you all
徐兄，请就位
Mr Tsui, please take your place
嗨    嗨
-Hello
-Hi
计算的方法采三局两胜制
The one who wins 2 games
out of 3 will win
每胡出例牌一副
For the winner in each game will receive
可得福禄寿神像一尊
A figurine of the gods of luck,
prosperity and longevity
三尊神像取得其二就是胜利者
Getting two figurines will win the game
南
South
北
North
打晚一点你会死吗？
Really mean business, huh?
东
East
碰
Pung
西
West
碰
Pung
打这章就完蛋了
This will finish the game
看起来，南北都让人扣死了
Looks like l am cornered
这次只有斧底抽薪了
All l can do is to withdraw fuel
from boiling cauldron
北
North
看来她没办法胡大四喜了
Looks like she hasn't the chance to win
南
South
碰，一筒
Pung, 1 Circle
她刚刚打过北，没有摸过牌
She just played north,
and hasn't taken a tile
这章北不会输的
This would not lose
北
North
真是想不到
l didn't expect that
北都会有得胡，谢了
lt's lucky to Mah Jongg with the North
小四喜，例牌
Three of Wind Group
根叔，拿个福给她
Uncle Gun, give her a lucky figurine
是，老爷
Yes, master
这招真高，媚姨真有两下子
Aunt May has good skills
是啊，没两下子怎么敢上台打呢？
Of course,
how can she compete otherwise !
燕先生，真不好意思
Sorry, Mr Yin
累到你面目无光
To have taken the colour from your face
现在打完了吗？
ls it over yet?
牌是没打完，不过不够班
No, but the incompetent
出闸脱脚
Lost at the start
坐穿梭机也追不上了
He can't catch up even on a jet
五筒
5 Circles
南
South
这边叫三六九四七
This side asking for 3,6,9,4,7
这边叫二五八
That side asking for 2,5,8
这铺牌听八章
l have 8 chances to win
想不胡都难
l must win
如果打九筒或者一筒
lf l discard 9 or 1 Circles...
输的机会是...
The possibility of losing...
打麻将还要用计算机呀？
Using a calculator for mahjong !
0.1666
如果打二五八筒
lf l discard 2,5,8 Circles
输的机会是0.250
The chances of losing are 0.250
如果打红中呢
lf l played the red middle tile
输的机会是
The chances of losing are...
0.08333
打得过
lt'd be best to discard this
红中
Red Dragon
就算她一手都是筒子
Even all the tiles are Circles
最多听八番
She can get 8 points the most
红中
Red Dragon
这小子搞什么鬼？
What is this kid doing?
现在想都不用想了，九子连环
Think no more.
t's Calling Nine Tile Hand
红中
Red Dragon
见鬼了，听八章摸第九章
Hell, draw the unwanted one
不要那章来那章
Draw the unwanted one
一筒
1 Circles
碰
Pung
听八章都胡不过你，真是见鬼
lt's bad luck losing to you
with such good chances
听八章的出冲给听九章的胡
The possibility of you losing to me is...
百分率是0.000134857
0.000134857
真是不容易啊
That's not easy
北
North
碰
Pung
九筒
9 Circles
碰
Pung
西
West
西也没出，他们两个一定对死
Looks like they're cornered
大家都难胡了
No one will win
现在就只剩七章牌
Only 7 tiles left for drawing
如果我开杠就二对一
lf l Kong than Johnson...
不开杠就二对二
will have greater chances to win
二万
Twenty Thousand
老不死的
You old fool
早不开，晚不开
Doing it at the wrong time
本来我海底捞月的
l can draw the last tile
现在没有牌摸了
Now there are no more tiles
还摸一章这样的牌回来
And to get this tile
全部生章
This one not discarded before
打发财，红中
lf l discard Green or Red Dragon
输给那小子对碰的机会多两倍
Will double the chances
of losing to the kid
打白板
lf l discard White Dragon
最多输给两家绝章单吊
l will lose to other player
白板
White Dragon
媚姨，的确很难打
Aunt May, it is difficult indeed
真是难为你了
lt's really hard on you !
庄臣，以后好好管理我那些生意了
Johnson,
take care of my business hereafter
不太对
Something's wrong
你干爹对你不错
Your Godpa treats you well
庄臣...
Johnson...
我终于赶来看你了
We have at last arrived
师傅，师傅
Teacher, teacher
我赢了，师傅
l've won, teacher !
那就好了
That's great
抗议，我抗议
l protest
丘本立很明显帮他干儿子
lt is obvious Yau is helping him
这是个骗局
This is a set up
你们看，丘本立出千
Yau is cheating, look
你们大家主持公道
You be the judge
难道我不要胡也算出千吗？
Does this count for cheating?
你不照规矩打就是出千
Not playing by the rules is cheating
你暗杠一条
You hid Kong 1 bamboo
里面三章全是发财
But the three tiles are Green Dragon
看不出你德高望重
Under your dignified appearance
居然使出这种卑鄙手段
You use such lowly tricks
你淫妻女，意图夺产
You commit adultery
& want to grab other's property
那又算什么？
How about that?
一笔归一笔
The two issues are separate
不要混在一起讲
Let's not confuse them
问题是你怎么向雀林高手交待？
The point is how can you account
to all experts
这些是家事
This is a family affair
我不需要向任何人交待
l don't need to be answerable to anyone
不过，我现在向各位礼貌的说一声
However l will say politely to all
庄臣就是我所有产业的继承人
Johnson is my sole heir
既然你替他出头
Since you stand up for him
有种就再打一铺
See if you have the guts
to play once more
郭老兄
Brother Kwok
你觉得输得不服气吗？
You don't admit defeat, do you?
为了使你心服口服
To convince you
我破例跟你玩一铺
l'll exceptionally play with you
好，不过要讲代价
OK, for a price
太大我玩不起的
l can't afford too high a stake
如果我输给你燕西楼
lf you lose the game to you
我郭柱马上掉头就走
l'll disappear
万一你输了
lf you lose...
你徒弟的所谓继承权就要还给丘太
Mrs. Yau will have the right
to Yau's estate
大家认为公不公道呀？
Do you all think this is fair?
公道
Fair
对不起，我做三元你做四喜
Sorry, we've a different combination
摸到一章你要的牌
l draw a tile you wanted
一条
1 bamboo
我也不好意思
l am sorry
你要的那章偏偏让我摸到了
l draw the tile you're after
东
East
六条
6 bamboos
东
East
八条
8 bamboos
九条
9 bamboos
发财
Green Dragon
西风
West
发财
Green Dragon
南风
South
白板
White Dragon
九条
9 bamboos
你反应倒挺快的
You sure have quick reflexes
知道马上转做十三么
And ability to adapt quickly
可惜，我比你先走一步
Unfortunately... l am one step ahead
白板
White Dragon
南风
South
六条
6 bamboos
北风
North
生章北风你都敢打
You dare to discard the North !
不怕输呀？
Aren't you afraid of losing?
看死他还没叫胡
l guess his combination isn't finished !
求和格
He asks for duel
一条
1 bamboo
难怪人家说先走先死
As they say,
one who moves first, dies first
一点儿都没错
lt is so accurate
燕先生
Mr Yin
为什么生章北风你还打？
Why did you discard the North?
你真傻
You are so dumb
大家摆明都做十三么
We both were making
the 13 Wonderful Lanterns
我拿死章九条
l get the last 9 bamboos tile
还有那章不敢打呢？
l can discard any tile
郭兄，服气吗？
Mr Kwok, you admit to losing now?
你够运气
You have good luck